为了完结本章，我想说几句关于应用RSA的
To conclude this module I want to say a few words about how RSA is used in practice.
首先如果大家想加速RSA加密
So first of all, if you want to speed up RSA encryption,
那么使用较小的公钥e是没有问题的
it's perfectly fine to use a small encryption exponent e.
可以不使用随机的e，而是选择一个小e
So rather than using a random e one can use a small value of e
事实上最小的可能值是e=3
and in fact the minimum value that's possible is e=3.
不难看出e的最小可能值
So it's not difficult to see that the smallest possible value for e
事实上e=3。我们来看为什么
is in fact e=3. And let's see why.
e=1是一个不好的想法，因为e=1的逆不难去求
Well e=1 is a bad idea because that's not particularly hard to invert with e=1.
e=2不是一个有效的RSA指数，因为记得在RSA的定义中
e=2 is not a valid RSA exponent because remember in the definition of RSA,
e必须与φ(N)互质。如果大家还记得，φ(N)=(p-1)(q-1)
e had to be relatively prime to phi(N). phi(N), if you remember, is (p-1) times (q-1),
是一个偶数。如果p和q都是奇数
which is an even number. If p and q are odd primes,
那么(p-1)(q-1)是一个偶数，但如果e是偶数，如果e=2
(p-1) times (q-1) is an even number, but if e is even, if e is equal to two,
e就不与φ(N)互质，那么e=2也不是有效的
it's not going to be relatively prime to phi(N). So e=2 is not valid either.
那么e=3是第一个最小的可以使用的值
And then e=3 is the first minimum value that can be used,
然后我们必须确保事实上，p=2 mod 3
and then we just have to make sure that in fact, p is
equal to two mod three,
q=2 mod 3，这样(p-1)(q-1)就不会被3整除
and q is equal to 2 mod 3 so that (p-1) times (q-1) is not divisible by 3.
那么事实上这是一个可使用的很好的公钥指数
So in fact this is a fine public exponent to use,
不过推荐的值是2^16+1，即65537
however the recommended value is 2 to the 16  plus 1. So 65537.
使用这个推荐的e值是个好点子
It's a good idea to use this recommended value of e.
计算x^3 mod N，你需要三步乘法
To compute x^3 mod N, you would basically need three multiplications.
而计算x^65537 mod N，使用重复平方算法，需要17步乘法
To compute x^65537 mod N using repeated squaring, you would need 17 multiplications.
你重复平方16次
Basically what you would do is you would repeatedly square 16 times
然后再乘一次x
and then you would multiply by x one more time.
那么只要17次乘法，你就可以计算出这个指数
Ok? So just with 17 multiplications you can do this exponentiation,
那么这比使用一个随机e要好得多了
so this is still much, much faster than using a random e,
随机e需要约2000次乘法
which would require something like 2000 multiplications.
那么这就让我们得到了RSA的非对称性
So this leads us into what's called the asymmetry of RSA,
事实上加密是很快的：加密只需要17次乘法
where in fact encryption is quite fast: encryption only requires 17 multiplications.
但是解密要慢得多
However decryption is much, much, much slower;
它需要约2000次乘法
it requires something on the order of 2,000 multiplications.
我应该指出，有一个标准的加速RSA解密的技巧
I should point out that there is a standard trick for slightly speeding up RSA decryption.
叫做RSA-CRT；叫做带中国剩余的RSA
This is called RSA-CRT; this stands for RSA with Chinese remaindering.
这个方法可以让RSA解密加速4倍
It's a method for speeding up RSA decryption by about a factor of four,
但不管如何这依然比加密慢很多
but nevertheless it's still gonna be much, much, much slower than encryption.
RSA的加密与解密的速度比，差不多从10到30
The ratio of encryption to decryption on RSA is roughly a factor of ten to thirty,
那么加密速度可以是解密的30倍，取决于模的大小
so encryption could be up to like thirty times faster than decryption, depending on the size of your modulus.
有趣的是，这是一个RSA的特殊性质，加密比解密快很多
Interestingly, this is a special property of RSA where encryption is so much faster than decryption.
另一公钥系统，比如说，我们下一章要看到的ElGamal加密
And other public key systems--for example, in the
next module we're gonna look at ElGamal encryption--
就没有这个性质，它的加密和解密用时差不多一样
don't have this property where both encryption and decryption take roughly the same amount of time.
我们之前已经讨论了RSA的密钥长度
We've already discussed key lengths for RSA before.
那么我只是想展示一下这些数，以提醒大家，
如果你使用128位AES密钥
So I just wanted to flash these numbers to remind you that if you're using a 128-bit AES key,
你应该使用一个3000位的模
really, you should be using a 3,000-bit modulus.
尽管大家都用2048位模
Although everybody just uses a 2,048 bit modulus.
如果你真使用一个长AES密钥，比如256位，那么RSA模将会很大
And if you're really using a long AES key, like a 256 bit AES key, the RSA modulus gets to be quite big.
现在我想提一下众多的针对RSA实现的攻击
Now, I wanted to mention a number of implementation attacks on RSA.
这些攻击已经针对特定的
These are attacks that have been demonstrated against particular,
RSA的数学上正确的实现成功展示了。但是这些实现
mathematically correct implementations of RSA. However, these implementations were vulnerable
对特定的旁道攻击是脆弱的，这使得这实现是完全不安全的
to certain side channel attacks that make the implementation completely insecure.
第一个例子是Paul Kocher于1997年提出的
So the first example of this is due to Paul Kocher back in '97.
他展示了一个计时攻击，你只需要测量RSA解密的时间
He showed a timing attack where all you do is you measure the time for an RSA decryption.
通过简单地测量耗时，你可以揭露密钥指数d
And simply by measuring the time, you can actually expose the secret exponent d.
那么，这是说如果你实现了RSA解密
And so, this says that if you are going to implement an RSA decryption,
你最好确保解密时间与这些参数无关
you had better make sure that the decryption time is independent of the arguments.
Paul Kocher两年后提出的另一个攻击展示了
Another attack also by Paul Kocher two years later showed that
如果你有一个智能卡，上面实现了RSA解密
if you have a smart card that's implementing RSA decryption
你可以测量这张卡在做RSA解密时的功耗
you can actually measure the power consumption of the card while it's doing RSA decryption
通过观察功耗峰谷，你可以读出d的各位
and then simply by looking at the peaks and troughs you can literally read off the bits of d
一次读一位，当智能卡在运行重复平方算法时
one bit at a time as the smart card is running through the repeated squaring algorithm.
那么使用一个功耗分析的攻击，是容易获得密钥各位的
So using a power analysis attack it's actually fairly easy to get the secret bits
除非智能卡能抵抗这些功耗攻击
of the secret key unless the smart card defends against power analysis attacks.
最后，另一种叫做错误攻击的展示了，RSA对解密错误是脆弱的
And finally another attack called a fault attack shows that the RSA is very vulnerable to
特别地，如果出于某些原因，RSA解密时发生了某个错误
decryption errors and in particular, if for some reason an error occurs during an RSA decryption,
一个错误将完全泄漏密钥了
one error is actually completely enough to reveal the secret key.
所以这个攻击事实上是很重要的，就是说，
一个错误将完全泄漏你的密钥
So this attack is actually fairly significant. It's just, one error completely reveals your secret key.
因此，许多密码学库都会检查RSA解密的结果
And as a result, many cryptolibraries will actually check the result of the RSA decryption
在返回结果给调用者之前。检查的方法是
before returning it to the caller. And the way you would check it is,
取这个指数的输出，计算它的e次方
you would take the output of this exponentiation, and simply raise it to the power of e,
检查是否又回到了c mod N
and check that you actually get back c modulo N.
如果是这样，说明这个解密是正确的
And if so, you know that your decryption was done correctly.
现在可以这么做的原因是，e比d小得多
Now the reason you can do this is because again, e is much smaller than d,
因此检查比计算d次方要花少得多的时间
therefore checking takes much less time than actually raising something to the power of d.
不过，即使检查比实际解密快十倍
Nevertheless, you know, even though checking is ten times faster than the actual decryption,
这依然引入一个10%的开销，所以有时这一功能实际上被关闭了
this still introduces a 10% slowdown. And so sometimes this is actually turned off.
不过，检查RSA输出的计算是否正确，的确是个好办法
But nevertheless, it's actually a good idea to check that your RSA output is correctly computed.
那么所有这些攻击再次说明了，如果你自己实现了一个RSA
And so all these attacks kind of again make the point that if you just implement RSA naively
它是数学上正确的，它能工作
it would be mathematically correct, it would work,
但是针对实现，依然会有这些潜在的攻击
however there would be all these potential attacks on the implementation
因此，你不应该自己去实现RSA
and as a result you should never implement RSA yourself.
始终使用标准密码库，始终使用已有的实现
Always, always use standard libraries and just use the implementation available there.
具体地说，我想给大家展示一个这些攻击的例子
So to be concrete, I wanted to show you an example of one of these attacks.
特别地，我会给大家展示RSA上的错误攻击
And in particular I'll show you the fault attacks on RSA.
这也是个错误攻击，是针对带中国剩余的RSA的
And again, this will be a fault attack on what's called RSA with Chinese remaindering.
事实上，如我在本节开头所说，RSA解密经常是如下实现的
So in fact, as I said at the beginning of the segment, RSA decryption is often implemented as follows:
解密密文c mod p，然后解密密文c mod q
What you do is, you decrypt the cipher text c modulo p, then you decrypt the cipher text c modulo q.
然后结合两者得到模N的解密
And then you combine the two to actually get the decryption modulo N.
这个组合是通过中国剩余定理做到的
And this combination is done using what's called a Chinese remainder theorem.
我这里不解释细节，不难看出这是如何工作的
Which I'm not going to explain here but it's not too difficult to see how that works.
一旦你有了模p和模q的解密的结果
Basically, once you have the result of the decryption mod p and the decryption mod q
把它组合起来获得模N下的解密
you can combine it to get the decryption mod N.
实际上这给出了一个4倍的加速
And it turns out this gives about a factor of four speed up
比起直接使用模N指数的实现来说
over the naive implementation of directly doing the exponential modulo N.
好，那么我们看为什么这对错误是脆弱的
Okay. So, let's see why this is vulnerable to faults.
假设当你的解密算法库在计算模q解密时
Suppose it so happens that when your decryption library is computing the decryption modulo q,
出于某些原因，处理器犯了一个错误
for some reason the processor makes an error.
实际上这不是一个正确的xq，得到的是错误的xq
And, actually, what it gets is not the correct xq. It gets an incorrect xq,
那么我们叫这个为xq^，不过当它计算模p的解密时
so let's call this xq hat. However when it computed the decryption modulo p,
没有错误发生，那么这些错误很少发生
you know, no error occurred. So these errors are fairly infrequent.
我们只假设，计算一个质数模时，发生了一个错误
And so let's just assume that an error occurred modulo one prime
计算另一个质数模时，没有发生错误
but it did not occur modulo the other prime.
如果我们计算模p是正确的，而计算模q是错误的
Well, if that's the case our computation is correct modulo p and incorrect modulo q.
那也就是说，当我们组合这两个结果后，我们会得到一个输出
That says when we combine the two results we're actually going to get an output,
我叫它x'，这个输出模p是正确的
I'll call it x prime, such that the output is correct modulo p.
x' = c^d mod p，但模q是错误的
So, x prime is really equal c to the d mod p but is incorrect modulo q.
如果我们计算这两个方程的e次方，我们获得下面这两个关系
If we raised both these equations to the power of e, what we obtain is the following two relations.
我们看看。这个我计算e次方
Well, let's see. This guy we raise it to power of e.
左边变成了x'^e
What happens is the left hand side becomes x prime to the e.
右边现在是c^d
The right hand side, here, it's c to the d.
如果我计算c^d的e次方，e和d，记得它们互为逆元
If I raise c to the d to the power of e--e and d, remember are inverses of one another--
因此，如果我计算c^d的e次方，两个指数相消，我就还原了c
And as a result, if I raise c to the d to the power of e, both exponents cancel out and I simply get c back.
所以我知道x'^e = c。但模q时，就有错误了
So I know that x prime to the e is equal to c. But modulo q, there was a mistake.
那么x'^e不等于c mod q
So x prime to the e is not equal to c modulo q.
因此，如果我看这个差，x'^e-c
So therefore, if I look at this difference, x prime to the e minus c.
我们知道它模p是0，而模q非0
We know that it's zero modulo p, and it's not zero modulo q.
那么现在如果我们计算这个值与N的gcd，能得到什么？
So now if we compute the GCD of this value with N, what do we get?
如我所说，这是模p为0的，但不是模q为0的
Well, as I said, this is zero mod p, but it's not equal to zero mod q.
意味着这里的量可以被p整除，而不可以被q整除
Which means that this quantity here is divisible by p, but is not divisible by q.
所以当我计算gcd时，我就会得到p
So therefore when I compute the GCD, what I'll get is simply p.
这是因为p能整除这个量，而q不能整除这个量
And again, this is because p divides this quantity here when q does not divide this quantity.
那么现在我只是获得了N的因子分解
So now basically what I have just obtained is the factorization of N.
我一旦获得N的因子分解，我就可以计算φ(N)了
Once I have the factorization of N I can compute phi(N)
那么有了φ(N)我就可以自己根据公钥，来计算解密指数了
and then given phi(N) I can actually compute myself the decryption exponent from the public key.
那么现在我已经根据公钥还原了私钥
So now I have just recovered the secret key from the public key
源起一个解密是发生的错误。这就是为什么
from a single mistake that happened during decryption. So this is why typically
当你解密RSA时，对结果进行检查是个好想法
when you do RSA decryption it's a good idea to check the results
特别是当你使用带中国剩余的RSA解密时
especially when you use Chinese remaindering to speed up RSA decryption.
我想讨论的最后的攻击是一个最近的发现
The last attack I want to talk about is a very recent observation
由Heninger和Lenstra等人观察得出的
that was observed by Heninger et al and Lenstra et al
证实了RSA密钥生成算法可能是有问题的，当它的熵不够时
that shows that RSA key generation can be problematic when it's done with bad entropy.
(熵不够意味着随机性不强)
这里会发生错误。那么OpenSSL生成RSA密钥的方法如下
So here's how things go wrong. So the way open SSL generates RSA keys is as follows.
开始时，先给这个伪随机数发生器以种子
Well, it starts by basically seeding the pseudo random number generator.
然后他使用了伪随机数发生器生成的随机字符串，
来生成第一个质数p
And then it uses random bits from a pseudo random number generator to generate the first prime p.
他还会继续给(伪)随机数发生器种子
Then it will go ahead and seed the random number generator some more,
然后从伪随机数发生器生成q
and will generate bits from the pseudo random number generator to generate q.
最后，它会输出p和q的乘积
And finally, it will output the product of p and q.
我们看到，这两步是给伪随机数发生器种子
Okay so the two steps, where we see the seed the pseudo random number generator.
现在假设这个是在某个路由器或防火墙上实现了
Now suppose that this is implemented on a router or a firewall of some sort,
假设密钥生成正好是在防火墙启动后
and suppose that the key generation happens right after the firewall starts up.
那么防火墙启动了。在启动的同时，伪随机数发生器
So the firewall boots up. At the time of the boot, there's not a lot of entropy
还没有多少熵，因此
in the pseudo random number generator, and as a result
防火墙很可能生成的质数p来自于一个低熵的集合
the firewall is likely to generate a prime p that comes from a very low entropy pool.
这意味着这个p的可能取值不多
Which means that this p is gonna be one of a small number of possibilities.
不过，在我们生成了p之后，生成质数实际上花了不少时间
However, after we've generated p, generating the prime actually takes a little bit of time,
有几个毫秒。那么之后，防火墙生成的密钥会有更多熵
a few microseconds. And so, by then the firewall will have generated more entropy
在我们添加了更多的熵之后
and so after we add more entropy to the entropy pool,
质数q从更多熵的空间里生成，因此对这个防火墙来说是唯一的
the prime q say is generated from a much larger entropy pool and is therefore unique to this firewall.
现在问题是，许多不多的防火墙，如果它们生成一个RSA密钥
Now the problem is that many different firewalls if they generate an RSA key
这样的话，他们中的许多最后会使用同样的质数p，但q不同
in this way many of them will actually end up using the same prime p but a different prime q.
这是说，如果我们看两个不同的防火墙上的两个RSA模N1,N2
So what this says is that if we look at two RSA moduli from two different firewalls, N1 and N2.
如果我们计算N1和N2的gcd，它们有着不同的q，但是p一样
If we compute the GCD of N1 and N2, well both of them had different q's but the same p.
那么如果我们计算gcd，我们最后会得到一个N的因子分解
So if we compute the GCD, actually we will end up with a factorization of N,
还包括N1和N2，然后我们可以解出N1,N2的私钥了
of both N1 and N2 and then we can actually figure out the private key both for N1 and for N2.
那么这已经在实际中被观察了
So this has actually been observed in practice.
两组都查看了整个网络
Both of these groups, what they did is they scanned the web
还原了所有的用于众多网页服务器的公钥
and recovered all of the public keys out there that are used on various web servers.
他们计算了大量的gcd，使用了某些算法上的技巧
They then ran a massive GCD, using some arithmetic tricks
他们可以计算大量的公钥对N1和N2的gcd
they were able to compute this massive GCD of all pairs of public keys N1 and N2.
注意看，他们发现了有很多的这些密钥都有共因子
And lo and behold, they actually realized that a fair number of these keys have a common factor.
那么他们就可以分解这些模了
So they were actually able to factor these moduli.
那么在这个实验中，他们可以分解0.4%的SSL公钥
So in the experiment, they were actually able to factor about .4% of all public SSL keys.
这是一个惊人的事实，这么多的网页服务器公钥都是脆弱的
This is an amazing fact, that, in fact, so many web server public keys out there
只是因为它们使用了低熵的RSA密钥
are vulnerable just because they happened to generate the RSA key using low entropy.
这样它们就与其他公钥有了共因子
So they have a common factor with somebody
else's factor
计算两者的gcd会得出它的因子分解
and GCDing the two together gives you the factorization.
那么这里的教训是当生成密钥时
So, the lesson from all this is when you generate keys,
无论它们是RSA密钥，还是ElGamal密钥，还是对称密钥
no matter whether they are RSA keys or ElGamal keys or symmetric keys,
重要的是你的发生器的种子是合理选取的
it's crucial that the number--, that your generator is properly seeded.
所以不要在机器刚刚启动时就生成密钥。必须确保
So don't generate keys immediately after start up. You have to kind of make sure
发生器的取种需要充分的时间来获得足够的熵
the seeding of the generator has had enough time to actually generate enough entropy.
然后才能开始生成密钥。那么这是一个很好的例子
And only then you can start generating keys. So this is a really nice example
一个坏的(伪)随机数发生器可以把你的RSA公钥搞砸
of how a, a bad random number generator can mess up your RSA public keys.
好，我们对RSA的讨论到这里就先告一段落了
Okay so this is the end of our discussion of public encryption from RSA.
我想提几篇进一步的阅读文献，如果大家想了解更多内容的话
I wanted to mention a few further readings if you want to read more about this.
这篇Victor Shoup的论文讨论了
So there's a nice paper by Victor Shoup that talks about why
选择密文安全对公钥密码是如此的重要
chosen cipher text security is so important in the public key settings.
以至于如果Bleichenbacher攻击不够有说服力，还有许多其他攻击
So if the Bleichenbacher attack wasn't convincing enough, there are many other attacks like this
比如这个，如果你不使用选择密文安全的系统
that are possible if you don't use a chosen cipher-text secure system.
那么如果你想学习更多关于选择密文安全的知识
So if you want to learn more about chosen cipher-text security,
请看Victor Shoup的论文
please look at Victor Shoup's paper.
我想我几年前写了一篇综述，讨论了许多RSA系统上的
There's a survey that I guess I wrote a couple years ago, that looks at many different attacks
不同的攻击。我想我写这篇综述时，RSA才问世20年
on the RSA system. I guess I wrote this when RSA was twenty,
我其实需要更新这三十年来的RSA系统的攻击了
I actually need to update this to 30 years of attack on the RSA cryptosystem.
过去十年有了新发展，但这篇还可以看
There've been some developments in the last decade, but for now this is actually a decent survey
可以用来了解更多的针对RSA的攻击
to look at and read about more attacks on RSA.
我提过的关于OAEP的结果，是引用的这篇
The OAEP results that I mentioned are referenced here, OAEP reconsidered.
最后如果大家对RSA和其他公钥系统的密钥长度分析感兴趣
And finally, if you're interested in key length analysis of RSA and other public key systems,
Arjen Lenstra有一篇很好的论文，讨论了你应该如何
there's a nice paper by Arjen Lenstra that discusses how you should choose
为你的公钥系统选取合适密钥长度，即使你是在使用对称密钥系统
key lengths for your public key systems, and even for your symmetric key systems.
好，就这四篇参考。希望大家有时间看看
Okay, so those are the four references. I hope you have time to look through them.
我就讲到这。下一章我们看
And I will stop here. And, in the next module we're going to look at
另一族公钥加密系统，这次是基于离散对数问题的
another family of public key encryption systems, this time based on discrete log.